This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
>> Hi everyone, this is Priyanka Ragan for
software engineering radio and my guest
today is Brigittita Bachler and the
topic is harness for coding agents. Rita
is a principal consultant and a software
developer with thoughtworks and is
passionate about helping teams and
organizations break down complexity and
find new perspectives to look at their
systems. She's a frequent conference
speaker and podcast guests on many
platforms. You can just Google her or
YouTube her. And welcome to the show,
Priita.
>> Yeah. Hi, Priyanka. Thanks for inviting
me.
>> Is there anything in your bio that you
would like the audience to know other
than what I've mentioned here? Yeah,
maybe the thing that's interesting is
what my current role is or what my role
has been for the past over two and a
half years at Thoughtworks. So, in 2023,
Thoughtworks decided to introduce a
full-time role for somebody to just look
into the topic of using generative AI or
language models for software delivery
and how it changes that. We're a
consultancy, so we have to always keep
our advice up to speed and speed is
definitely something that's happening a
lot in the space. So yeah, I'm a
distinguished engineer there and I've
basically been fully immersed full-time
in this space for the last 2 and a half
years and so kind of seen the history.
Okay, great. So that will bring us right
into our show at software engineering
radio. We've done a few shows on AI and
software development whether it's
episode 711 with Scott Hanselman on AI
assisted tools. We did an episode 603
with Rishi Singh on using Gen AI for
test code generation and episode 693 on
AI assisted debugging. So before we
start the show we thought we'll spend
some time on the first part of the show
where we'll go through some definitions
and I'm heavily quoting here from the
article you wrote on harness
engineering. Mhm.
>> So to start with what exactly is harness
and harness engineering and how is it
different from say prompt engineering or
context engineering? I mean, as I just
mentioned and as everybody's feeling
right now, this space is like really
fast evolving and one of the challenges
there is what language we're all using,
right? I [clears throat] mean, we can
come up even faster with stuff as well,
right? So, we're all throwing lots of
terms out there and I think that's been
a challenge for me like to find the
right words to describe what is
happening because that also helps me
think about it better, right? And this
word harness, it has gone through a
little bit of an evolution, but recently
it's increasingly being used for
describing something that sits on top of
a language model and orchestrates
everything that we want to do with the
model, right? So it has a system prompt.
It can ask the language model for tool
calls and stuff like that. Right? So
basically what we've also been calling
an agent and then when we talk about a
coding harness like that as examples
that would be like claw code or cursor
or the pi coding harness. So
increasingly people are calling that
harness right and then in combination
with the model when you run it it
becomes an agent right so I'm almost now
starting to think of like an agent as
something that is like an instance of
something running and maybe harness is
the tool the skeleton of what runs it
right like so that's where my head is at
now right and then so harness
engineering is like how you make those
harnesses better so for example in a
coding harness you can make it better by
thinking about providing it with
different tools or there's like other
schools of thought where you make it
better by providing it with less tools
and with less complexity. Right? So
there's these different approaches of
how to make the coding harness better.
But then the part that I wrote about in
my article is about the users of the
coding harness. So us or me as an
application developer, I'm using cloud
code as a coding harness and I'm trying
to extend the harness for my specific
codebase. Right? So I'm trying to give
the harness, the agent, whatever we want
to call it, like even more information,
even more tools specifically to my
application that I'm working on to make
the results better. So that's like it's
almost like an onion multiple layers
type of thing. So first I choose the
base harness that I'm going to use, for
example, cloud code, and then I give it
even more stuff like skills and tools
and stuff like that to get the results
that I want for my situation. I think
the timing seems apt because most people
are now using AI coding agents and AI
agents for doing all of the coding work
and I guess the question I wanted to ask
you is when do you feel there's a need
to have a harness? Is it immediately as
soon as you start coding with the coding
agent? I mean the coding harness itself
you need right like that's the coding
agent basically that's what I was saying
there's the terms that people use are
changing right now a little bit right
but when I think about that expanded
harness you can totally start without
anything and I see this also as a
barrier that some people now who are
coming to aentic coding a bit later
maybe and there's like all of this
tooling and all of these terms and like
it's almost like some people before they
even want to start they ask oh what
skills do I need what should I put into
the agent MD it's almost like they're
afraid to get started because it feels
like there's this whole discipline of
how to use these things, right? But you
can absolutely just get started plain
vanilla without putting anything in
there. And I would actually recommend it
when you first do a gentic coding just
to like feel what it actually does
without it. Right? So it's like a big
skill that we now need as developers, I
think, to understand what's actually
going on, what tools are already there,
like how does this tool work out of the
box? Like I said before, it might be
quite different using cloud code or
cursor versus like a much more
lightweight harness like the pi coding
agent, right? So getting a feeling for
what already works without putting
anything in there. The models have
gotten a lot stronger. I feel like some
people have already built up skills and
lots of instructions might want to
revisit that as well with newer models
because some things are maybe not
necessary anymore, right? So it's worth
understanding what it feels like to work
with them without your custom stuff and
then build your own stuff up step by
step on top of that.
>> So you describe as the harness as
something that goes around the model,
right? So can you break it down to us?
For example, in the article you talk
about these things called as guides and
sensors. Can you break that down for us?
>> Yeah. So this again is all about like I
was trying to come up with vocabulary
for us to talk about this. Right. So
this is not necessarily new stuff. in
particular the part that I call guides.
So by guides I mean everything that we
feed forward into the agent. So we try
to anticipate both what we want it to do
but also what we do not want it to do
and we write it down. Right? So this is
what lots of people are already doing
and have been doing for quite a while.
It usually manifests in like a bunch of
markdown files. So the agents MD or the
claude MD file is the most prominent one
that has been around for quite a while.
And so we write into that file, I want
you to do this, I do not want you to do
that. Never ever do that. It's these
important important this type of stuff.
And it can actually be all kinds of
different guides, right? So it can be
normative ones, right? That set up the
norms and the conventions that we want
to use in this repository or it can be
informative, right? So it can describe
the context of the application, what
we're trying to achieve, describing what
the architecture is or stuff like that,
right? So it can be lots of different
things. And then on the flip side of
that, so this is like feed forward. We
anticipate and try to increase the
probability that it will do very well on
the first go, but it's often not perfect
on the first go, right? So then we want
to give it feedback as well. And that's
like what in the article I call the
sensors. So there we think about what
sensors do I want to make available so
that it can selfcorrect before I even
have to look at it and find all of these
maybe even small hygiene type of things,
right? And a sensor can be both another
large language model or like the large
language model itself, right? So a
sensor can be a skill that has code
review instructions, right? That again
tells it we want this, we don't want
that. This is bad, this is good. But a
sensor can also be something
computational, right? Something that
actually runs on the CPU, not on the
GPU. So that would be something like
static code analysis or our test suite
or coverage data or any of those types
of things. And on the feed forward side
by the way we can also have
computational guides. So the most
powerful example of that I would say is
that of code mod tools. So those are
tools like open rewrite is very
prominent in that area. There are a
bunch of those in the JavaScript space
as well. And so code mod tools basically
can do like mass refactoring, mass
changing of your codebase, right? And
there are lots of case studies and use
cases out there where you combine
language models and these code mods as
extra guides to do migrations and
upgrades and stuff like that, version
upgrades that require a lot of stuff,
right? where this computational guide
can maybe cover like 80 90% of the work
and then the rest of the is a bit more
semantic and the large language model
fills in there. Right? So the guides are
all about increasing the probability
that it does a good job in the first
place and then the sensors are about
giving it direct feedback and maybe a
little bit of additional guidance to
selfcorrect.
>> So do you feel that the role of the
feedback loops makes the code more
reliable?
>> Yeah, definitely. I mean, there's a
school of thought that the language
models will just get better and better
and better until they're just perfect at
coding and the code will always be
perfect, right? But yeah, I don't think
that's realistic or like if it ever gets
to that point that we do have setups
that can write good code almost all of
the time. I think it will have to
involve these types of sensors to help
the model correct. also in like the
existing big experimental and less
experimental stuff like where people
orchestrate lots and lots of agents that
just collaborate with each other and
they're orchestrated and they go off and
do a task. There's also a lot of
sensoring going on, right? There's
sensoring with the C almost like each
other, right? So yeah, I think they play
a huge role and in my experimentation
that I've done with for example static
code analysis, we can go into that a bit
later if you want or like checking for
coupling lots of stuff about
maintainability of software. I've
definitely seen them kick in a lot even
when I was using powerful models to do
the coding. So yeah, there's always like
little flaws the same as when we as
humans write code and it's just like a
great feedback mechanism. Are
architectural constraints good guard
rails for AI agents?
>> Yeah, I actually write in the article
about how to me there's different
dimensions that we can think through for
the guides and sensors, right? Like what
are the things we want to regulate for,
right? So I was thinking about some
parallels to cybernetics that like the
code base that we're generating is
actually like something that we're
regulating, right? And so these
different things that we're regulating
can be maintainability for example. So
trying to make the risk of a change in
the future as low as possible or it can
be architecture fitness right so
thinking about sensors and also guides
that describe what we want in the
architecture and then sensors that check
if it's there right can be around the
typical illities and architecture
fitness functions like performance and
those types of things or in a way you
could say architecture is also people
often call the codebased design
architecture as well right so that could
be about coupling and stuff like that
which maybe goes in the direction of
maintaining ability again and then of
course another big thing that we want to
regulate is that the code actually does
what we want it to do right so like
functional correctness but so yeah your
question about architecture like
depending on what one means by
architecture which is a big topic as
well but yeah I would say absolutely
yeah
>> I noticed something on Twitter a few
days back where someone said that they
tried to make a prompt very abstract and
then the AI agent didn't perform very
well
>> Mhm. So I guess it had to be at a level
where it could understand abstractness
it doesn't do very well with right so I
think in that sense it does make sense
about what you're saying about defining
the architectural constraints properly
so the AI agents can pick it up
>> yeah I mean it depends on what is meant
by abstraction right when you create an
abstract instruction that abstract means
with little detail right that could be a
problem but of course language models
are actually sometimes good at doing
abstractions right it's sometimes all
that they do because they translate
stuff right they translate from one
thing to another so I think it depends
on what is meant by abstraction in that
context but you were also initially
asking me what's the difference between
harness engineering and prompt
engineering and context engineering I
would say it's all different forms of a
similar thing right so I mean we started
2 and a half 3 years ago with saying
prompt engineering super important right
like exactly how you craft your prompt
and where you put stuff and you give the
agent or the LLM a role and which order
do you put it? And that has become a lot
less important with the big models,
right? If we want to go back to smaller
models, which there are lots of good
reasons for it might be more important
again, right? Then we came to context
engineering which is all about
integrating ideally the information that
the model so you tune the information
that you give to the model in a way that
you get better results. And I think
harness engineering is a specific form
of that. So with guides you tune
information and instructions right and
then with the sensors again you give it
information. So I think it's a specific
form of context engineering but yeah
crafting the problems exactly is not as
important anymore with the latest
models. So harness engineering it can be
also coupled with all these traditional
practices like unit testing integration
testing CI/CD and static analysis.
Right.
>> Mhm.
>> Can you talk a little bit about that?
>> Yeah. So that's what I've been
experimenting a lot with on the sensors
side of things, right? So we have a lot
of existing tools actually that we can
use and now make available to these
agents and interestingly some of those
tools that we have we have not used a
lot in the past as humans right so
static code analysis for example I'm a
consultant right so I've seen lots of
different organizations build software
and I often see them having a setup of
code analysis like a sonar server
somewhere in the corner but then it's
not really being monitored or used and I
think one of this maybe two main reasons
one of them is that I think especially
experienced developers are aware that it
can only do so much right like it's not
like a llinter can actually like
guarantee the quality and changeability
of a codebase in the future but the
other thing is also that it often
becomes noise overload right like or the
signal to noise ratio was often not very
good right so you get like even when you
use them from the beginning in a
codebase you often get like overwhelmed
by all the messages and you don't want
to like fine-tune every single one where
you want to make an exception or not.
So, you just like get overwhelmed by it,
right? And I think there's a new
opportunity now with large language
models and with coding agents to maybe
get through that and actually have like
a good baseline that is always clean
with the analysis methods because what
you can do is you can write custom
messages for these lint messages, right?
So let's take an example the very common
pitfall or a very common failure mode of
AI coding agents as well. Functions that
have too many lines that are too long,
right? Like max lines per function or
whatever. I was doing this with ESLint
in a TypeScript codebase. So it was max
lines per function. So now I overwrote
the message that comes back. It doesn't
just say this function is 120 lines
long. We only allow X lines long. But it
also says this might be a smell. Please
consider if we should refactor this, if
we should split this up, if this
function is doing too many things, make
a judgment call. But if you decide that
it's okay that this function is five
lines longer or we just can't do
anything about it or it's just like a
test data function or whatever, then
you're allowed to create a rule that
increases that threshold for this
function. So you give the large language
model guidance and ask it to make a
judgment call. Right? So this makes it
explicit for me. I can actually review
and go through the places where it
increased the threshold and say I'm okay
with that, I'm not okay with that. But
this automatically does this tuning for
me, right? That I would usually never
suppress it directly in the code because
it's just too tedious when I was doing
it myself. But with the help of the
agent, I can actually try and get like a
clean slate all the time and then it
becomes a much better sensor.
>> Well, that's very interesting. You
talked a little bit about the lines of
code and I was thinking about the
cyclometric complexity which when we
wrote code as humans would be something
that we would have very hard targets on
and nowadays I noticed when I reviewing
code of someone who's generated the code
completely with AI if they don't have
say these constraints then you might see
cyclometric complexity like 125 or
something that's huge right that's
>> that feels like an seismic event or
something compared to say what we would
have it in. So for those kind of cases
is what you're saying that you can
actually add things in your guides to
restrict the agent. That's what you're
saying. So you can actually have sort of
an constraint that you can place on the
agent for your particular repository
like coding guidelines.
>> Yeah. So the sensor triggers another
little loop. So I define my constraints
in the configuration of the static code
analysis. For example, I say what my
maximum allowed cyclomatic complexity
is, right? Then the agent writes some
code and then the analysis tool says
over there cyclomatic complexity is too
high. And then it also has this
additional little prompt that tells it
more about how we wanted to handle
cyclomatic complexity with the whole
like you are allowed to increase it if
you make a judgment call that then rely
on the LLM a lot again. But it just
makes it more explicit where you need to
review and then that starts another
little loop where the agent tries to
self-correct and then asks the sensor
again, right? So it's an extra little
loop that you start and the facto
complexity definitely another great
example of a very typical failure mode
of AI generated code. So that one
triggered a lot for me as well, even
with the big models. And not just like
the complexity, but also sometimes just
very brittle, hard to read boolean
expressions, like combinations of
different that maybe as a human I would
have turned the does not equal around to
an equal or just doesn't feel very
expressive and very readable. And some
people say, "Oh, but it doesn't matter
if it's readable because AI changes it
in the future." But when you have these
weird boolean expressions, it's a lot
riskier for AI to change it as well in
the future and have like a unintended
side effect that breaks something else.
Right.
>> So what do you mean by AI change it in
the future? Do you mean by a refactoring
attempt?
>> Yeah. So some people say that all of
these things about like code readability
or code quality is not as important
anymore because as a human I will not
have to deal with the details anymore. I
just deal with like a little bit higher
level and AI will change the details in
the future. So it doesn't matter to me
if I'm able to read this boolean
expression but it turns out that AI
needs a lot of the same things that we
need to make safe changes to stuff.
>> Okay, got it. So what about even the
practices like unit testing and we
generate obviously use a lot of AI
agents to generate the test but one
thing I've noticed is sometimes when I
write the test as a human then the code
becomes better is that something that
you have seen in your experience because
I'm able to describe the behavior better
when I write a unit test and therefore I
feel the code gets generated better.
Yeah, I mean tests are definitely an
important sensor, but they have two
overarching roles. I mean there's
probably more but two I have in mind,
right? Like one is we try to use them to
check the functional correctness of what
we're building. Is it correct? And there
if we just have AI generate all the
tests and the code, then other than
doing manual tests and observing what
the application does, it's not 100%
guarantee that it actually does what we
want it to do, right? because we didn't
write the test. Test suites also have
another function as a regression sensor,
right? Just telling us how good are they
at telling us that something broke,
right? That's more a maintainability
concern. But that's also like an
interesting part of a sensor that we can
also talk about next if you want to. But
yeah, this whole thing about the
correctness of tests, I mean, the tests
might all be green, but just test things
that we don't want, right? And in the
past, like you said, we often like
that's why it's called testdriven
development, right? It wasn't just about
making sure we have tests, but it was
about writing the test first because the
tests are the ultimate specification,
right? They made us think through what
we actually want. And so this for me is
still like a largely unsolved problem,
let's say, because you might argue that
maybe we could say as a human, my main
role is to review the tests and okay,
let's say AI has gotten good at the
code. I have some sensors in place.
Maybe I'm exaggerating because that's
not enough. But let's say okay I don't
want to look at the code anymore but I
want to review the tests. But tests are
very tedious to review when you haven't
written them yourself, right? They're
very verbose and you have to like it's a
lot of detail and you actually want to
think about the big picture like have I
thought about everything, all the
combinations and stuff like that, right?
So I recently talked a lot to my
colleague Matio Vakari about this who
has been on some teams where he's trying
to look for a good acceptance test level
and then he's trying to find a way to
write those acceptance tests and their
input and outputs in particular in a way
that is really easy to review so that he
can really think about the input output
data that is very relatively easy to do
for example when you have HTTP when you
have APIs right there's always a request
and a response and you want to like have
different scenarios of requests and
response combinations that you test. In
other parts of the codebase, it's a lot
messier. Like there's different
combinations and unit tests. It's much
different. And then when you write these
acceptance tests, they're often not as
detailed as the unit tests. And so, do
you just leave the unit test to AI? I
mean, ultimately, it's a bit of a risk
assessment, a risk decision. In your
situation, how good do you think AI will
be at writing these unit tests? So I
think it's like a very unsolved problem
in a way but a very very important one
right it's all about thinking about our
feedback loops for the correctness of
what we're doing and they can be very
different depending on what type of
application you build right is it an API
is there a UI are you writing to a
database are you writing events that
need to land in some other system all of
those situation need very different type
of testing so it's also hard to find
just one simple way to do this Okay,
sounds good. I think let's move on to
some of practical implementation tips
and maybe we'll cover some of the
questions I had. The first thing I want
to ask you in this practical
implementation segment is what does a
minimum viable harness look like for a
new team? Can you give some tips and
tools to add? It's actually hard to
answer because this is like still so
much evolving. So also in the
experiments that I've been doing, I'm
just like poking around and trying to
use different sensors and to even see
like which of these are valuable, which
are not, right? And that's definitely
like one of the big questions here, the
meta questions as well. When you build
this harness, when you have these guides
and sensors in place, how do you know
that they're effective? It's like on the
guides side because the guides are often
inferential. So they're often like
markdown files that get interpreted by a
large language model. So on the guide
side, there are now some ways to do like
skills evals, right? So like to have
your skills and then write some
scenarios and run them one time with the
skill, one time without the skill and
see if the skill actually makes the
results better or if the model would
have been good at it by itself. Right?
That's the whole thing I said earlier
about the models getting more powerful.
And when you use a very powerful model,
you might not even need some of those
instructions, right? Especially like
when you think about that many skills
these days are actually generated by
large language models. So people have
large language models to generate the
skills. And then I'm sometimes like yeah
but then if the model already knows all
of this sometimes it's still useful. I'm
not saying it doesn't make sense, right?
But it sometimes makes me wonder is
there like some kind of cycle then I
should consider if it actually needs it
or not, right? Unfortunately models are
changing all the time their capabilities
as well. So eval that's one way to check
if your skills are actually being
effective on the sensor side especially
the computational sensors like the code
analysis and all of that that I was
talking about there's not really like
tooling for that yet right so I've been
experimenting a bit in a speculative
kind of way what type of tooling I would
want for this I'll write a bit about
that publicly soon but there I was also
thinking about okay during my coding
agent session I was giving it access to
all of these sensors in one big suite
and one big like let's say sidec car
that was running next to my agent and so
I had it write a history of every time
the agent checked for the state of the
sensors I had it write a history and
then I could see across the coding
session how did the test coverage evolve
how did the number of analysis
violations evolve and different security
static code analysis and stuff like that
as well and I would sometimes see that
in the middle of the session some issues
would come up and then they would go
away again so that's maybe the first
step to have some like observability of
what's going on with the sensors. And
then it's like a similar dilemma to our
pipelines. It's very similar to our
integration pipelines, right? If my
pipeline is always green, is that a good
thing? It's actually not, right? You
want it to go red sometimes because that
gives you the good feeling that oh yeah,
it's actually a safety net that works,
right? If it's always green, I would get
suspicious. But if it's red all the
time, that's also bad, right? So it's
kind of this dilemma of what level of
like the sensors firing and actually
giving feedback is good or bad. But that
would be something that would be great
in the future if we had more tools that
would introduce this type of
observability. There's a lot of that
happening in the base harnesses space
right so around what people are calling
agent traces. So there's a company
founded by the ex GitHub CEO called
Entire and they just like as their first
little thing they released a CLI that
helps you track all of the stuff that is
going on in a coding agent session so
that it can be analyzed later and
there's some other tooling popping up at
the moment around that. So that's
another way to look at how well is my
harness working. Once we figure out how
to analyze all of these traces of what's
going on in the session and can then
maybe compare when I have these guides
and sensors in place, I actually got to
my goal a lot faster than when I did
not. or can we I don't know how to
practically measure this but can we have
metrics around how long did the agent go
until I had to intervene or like how
much feedback would I give it before it
could actually create a commit or so I
think that's also an emerging space of
monitoring and analyzing how well our
coding agent sessions are going which
would tell us about the harness
effectiveness both of the base harness
that we're using so again cloud code pi
cursor and of the harness that we put
around it
>> yeah because sometimes I also notice
that the when you ask it to change a
particular file based on constraints as
you say there's changes all over the
place and sometimes it feels like you're
losing control of the file and every
time I'm always doing the diff pretty
slowly on the agent almost stopping it
at every time and checking the change.
So I think an observability log on the
changes would also be good sometimes
because sometimes it feels like it's all
over the place and it also completely
rewrites things cuz I've had a case was
it on last Friday where I was rewriting
a bunch of unit tests. the unit test was
not functioning okay and then I was
trying to go and investigate it and when
I investigated I found the exact part
where it was failing and I asked just
gave instructions to redo that part with
the correct logic and then the entire
stuff got overwritten you know
>> the other previous functions because I
had forgotten to say that you know
please do not change anything except
this even though I had it in my guide I
don't know so that can be sometimes
where you feel you're losing control
like the pace is very fast
>> and that also goes beyond single file
right like we talked about static code
analysis before a lot and the type of
analysis that I gave examples of was
mostly related to the file level right
or function level or something like that
cyclatic complexity and stuff like that
but we also usually as developers think
a lot about one level higher about cross
file cross module what is our coupling
and stuff like that Right? Because we
know that when that gets messy, changes
will get harder and harder and harder
and riskier and riskier in the future.
So for example, often when I use a
coding agent to let's say build up like
a P that I actually want to be
maintainable for a little while at
least, right? I start noticing that
after a while my change sets get bigger
and bigger because when I change
something, it has to change suddenly.
Like I did a change recently where I
just added a new query parameter to one
of the endpoints and it changed 15 files
I think. So this is a relatively small
application. So that was actually quite
a lot. So that's like a smell usually
for oh there's some repeatability here.
There's something that's not well
abstracted right. So and that's then
about like sensors thinking about
sensors that help us look at that
coupling and modularity level. Right? So
I tried that a little bit with again
like more computational static analysis
you know finding the what are the files
that get imported a lot by other files
or stuff like that and it's actually not
that helpful like it finds some of the
hot spots but in this area with
modularity I've had much better results
with LLM sensors LLM judges right that
actually have really good prompting
about what coupling and balanced
coupling means right let me just quickly
look I don't I don't want to bodgege the
name but I use this skill by Vlad Konov
who wrote a book about balance coupling
right and I've had really really good
results which shows when you have an
expert write really good description
about also like tradeoffs and semantic
analysis of what that means you can get
some good results from that it's not
just doing lots of stuff in one file
>> inside of a file when I feel confident
in my tests I sometimes don't mind as
much although it is a little suspicious
and then I go and look at that in
particular, but across files it's even
more problematic potentially. Right.
>> So, can you walk us through a real world
example of an harness in action?
>> So, I actually published a little
YouTube video recently on an example
like my example application that I'm
working on where I'm trying to put a
harness like that in there. And in that
one, because I focus a lot on sensors, I
don't have a lot of guides in there. But
I would say typically what I see lots of
teams do these days is like on the one
hand have thisformational part of the
guides, right? So almost like a
knowledge base inside the codebase that
gives the general context of the the
[snorts] basics of what you're working
on so that the agent becomes aware of
that really quickly and doesn't have to
like reconstruct that every time you
start a session by looking at the
codebase. And then the other part is
definitely some like coding conventions
or pitfalls that are maybe in cloud MD
or agents MD file and then maybe a few
skills that are about coding conventions
in places right on top of that there's
of course that whole space of specdriven
specificationdriven development right
where people then also use like
workflows and stuff like that which in a
way is also extra guides right but I
know that lots of people are building
their own workflows in form of guides
first do the planning then do the design
then do the you know all of those all of
those types of things. So that's also
quite typical but also a space that is
very emerging and lots of different
stuff's happening and there's some
backlash to it already again about like
how it's too much right with spectrum
development. So that's on the guide side
right on the sensor side I haven't seen
that as much yet but like in my
application that I've been using I've
set up like a set of sensors that happen
during the coding agent session. So for
example the static code analysis we
talked about it's looking at the test
coverage I have mutation testing set up
as well although that's a bit resource
intense right but mutation testing with
the coverage actually tells me how good
my regression level is right so there's
a bunch of things happening in the
session before I even do a commit I
should say I come very much from the
tradition of trunkbased development and
you know pushing to main as much as
possible so I'm very like controlling
about a commit and I always want it to
be perfect so I know that some people
are using much smaller commits and then
think more about the PR. I just wanted
to give that as a caveat. But this
exactly goes to like one of the things
we have to do when we think about the
guides and sensors is where to place
them, where do we want them to run?
Because they have different costs in
terms of how long they take to run, how
much energy they use to run, how many
tokens they use to run. So those are all
things to consider of where we place
them during the session before we even
integrate during a PR review or in the
CI/CD pipeline. And then there's also
one place in our path to production that
is kind of like a repeated running of
sensors. There's this article by an open
AI team about harness engineering where
they call this garbage collection. So
they say they worked on a codebase for
five, six months just having the agent
touch all the code and them just working
on that harness and they still saw
technical debt compound you know
probably also things like I experienced
about the modularity and stuff like
that. So they also have things running
on a schedule right like I don't know
they didn't share details about how
often they do that but in my application
I also have some skills that are like
one is this modularity review one is
like a security review that is based on
our internal infosc guidelines at
thoughtworks and then there's one that
checks kind of like the freshness of the
dependencies and gives me
recommendations of where I should
replace libraries or something like that
and I just go in there and I currently
manually just run those once a week and
see if there's anything new. You can of
course then expand that even more. Have
the agent create tickets for the
findings that it has or even create pull
requests for the findings that it has.
Right? So it all depends on your team
processes and how you're maintaining the
application. But you can already start
by just having it create a report once a
week and having a human look at it. It
has definitely reduced my maintenance
work on this application which is a real
life application with a very small user
base but you know it needs some
maintenance and it has definitely made
it possible for me to do that with like
half an hour a week or something like
that.
>> Okay, that's interesting to know. And
are there any frameworks or patterns for
building harnesses today?
>> No, on the one hand I think it's more
like conceptual thing. So there's
probably not here's like the one
technical thing that is the harness and
at least not in this like expanded
harness you know of course for the base
harness there's the one technical thing
that is the coding engine harness but
yeah I've also been thinking about that
for example you have guides and sensors
that have to be consistent with each
other right you might have a guide that
describes this is a very simple example
that's probably not real in reality but
let's say a guy said you should have
very low cyclomatic complexity and then
there's a sensor that actually checks
the cyroatic complexity right I mean
this is very simple example but just to
say that the guides and sensors they
have to be in sync with each other and
you might have them all like splattered
across the code base and not so I've
also been wondering is there a way to
maybe package them together somehow or
is there a way that the base harness can
take some of the responsibility of
running the sensors with some like
plugins or something like that right I
think there's definitely potential for
more tooling in some of these things and
more configur durability but overall I
think it will always stay more like a
conceptual thing like architecture or
like what are the things that you have
in place to increase your coding agents
quality of results
>> so this comes before you actually do the
like you run your GitHub actions or
anything on the main branch right so
when as soon as you get a result from
the coding agent is when you run these
sensors as well
>> like I said you have to decide where you
put which sensor right and I definitely
think there are definitely the kind of
lowhanging crude quick hygiene type of
sensors that also run really fast. Why
not run them before you even create a
commit? Like I see a lot of the base
harnesses always assume there's already
a PR or you're on a branch or something,
right? But I want to have a lot more
stuff that happens on my local change
diff, right? Because if you can do it
after the commit, you can also do it
before it, right? So again, maybe this
comes from my history of trunkbased
development, but we don't want to like
start pushing quality, right? We want to
keep it as far left as possible whenever
we can, right? So, especially the cheap
stuff, let's just try to run it, you
know, as soon as possible and not 2 days
later when we have a PR review.
>> And here is where I want to ask you a
question also in terms of when you run
these tools for doing the static code
analysis or security like say SGEP or
tools like that, what happens is
sometimes you'll get a finding where
it'll tell you to go and fix it. But
then the thing is that sometimes it
might not really make sense to fix it in
your particular project either because
of it could break something else or it's
really not that important and there's
almost a judgment that comes from a
human to tell you to fix it right how
does that work with the AI agents
>> so this goes back to what I was talking
about before where I was asking it to
make a judgment call in my
>> selfcorrection guidance so to say right
and so that again is you know remains to
be seen how much we trust the models to
make this judgment call. Right? We might
trust it more with something like max
lines per function than with like a
security thing. Right? So I actually
also do have Sam grabb set up for my
application. And I think in that
guidance I don't tell it to make a
judgment call. I tell it to let me know.
I don't quite remember. But in any case
it's a lot easier to do this like
suppression. You know like usually these
linting tools you can put like a comment
in the code and then in the comment you
can also say why you are suppressing it
right so that also gives information for
the future when you're doing this so
harnesses for me are all about improving
how as a human I can prioritize where to
put my review so always thinking about
like how can I triage that almost right
and depending on the risk that I see in
my use case in this area of the
application and so on but the thing that
I actually find even more interesting
than that and I don't know yet where
that is going to go is what if you have
sensors that contradict each other right
tradeoffs are all over software delivery
right so I have been like in my
application watching out for these like
are there any like contradictions
tradeoffs what does that mean the only
small thing I found maybe so far is that
because my agent has been doing a lot of
splitting things into smaller pieces
because of you know it kept violating
max lines per function max lines profile
kinds of things. So it puts some
reasonable exceptions in there, but
sometimes it just like breaks my React
components down even smaller and
smaller, right? And then suddenly I have
a hierarchy of I don't know how many
levels of React components that contain
each other and that they all like
suddenly pass through like eight or 10
properties all the way down to the
bottom and most components don't even
need that. Right? So, that's maybe the
only example I've seen of a trade-off so
far where the, you know, it's very eager
to break everything down into smaller
pieces because that's what the sensor
said. But what if I now switched on
another sensor that tells it more about
the React component health and like not
making it too granular? So, that will be
interesting to see when you switch on
like lots and lots of sensors, will it
just go into overdrive and keep ping
ponging between different judgment
calls?
>> Right. That's very interesting. So then
how do you kind of build trust in
systems where agents are generating and
also modifying so much of the code?
>> Yeah. So that's kind of the goal of
this, right? like thinking about the
like increasing the trust in the agent
and this is of course not the only thing
right like we were saying before the
test suite is green that might not
actually mean anything right but it is a
lot about probabilities and risk
assessment right so I always think of it
as probability impact and detectability
that's always like the formula of how
you do risk assessment so I think about
how probable do I think it is that AI
will do something wrong or will do it
right however I want to think about it
and so that probability assessment is
based on my experience with using the
coding agent my experience with using
the model how much do I know about the
tool so it's very like you can't just
look it up in a table it's very much
this skill that we have to own because
it's such a weird technology but
probability that it does something wrong
might also be oh this is a very very
messy code base so it's a lot higher
probability that it will do something
wrong than when it's like a very very
wellactored codebase. And then for
impact is all about the use case. Am I
building a PC or a spike or is this like
a super critical business flow that I'm
working on? And then detectability is
all about how easy will it be for me to
see that it did something wrong. So what
are my feedback loops? What do I have in
place? And then when I look at all of
those things, then I decide how much do
I let it go unsupervised? How much
review do I want to do? Do I want to
look at every single line of code or
just like a highle thing just check the
sensors and I'm done. And yeah to go
back to the probability right
probability then is also a lot about how
much confidence I have in my guides and
sensors how much visibility do I have
into the things that I care about for
this particular application and for this
change that I'm doing
>> so in a sense the trust gets built
because of your trust and also your
harness in a sense right
>> yeah yeah yeah we just now have to find
out like how far can we push these
harnesses and again it might depend on
the use case right and some use cases
I'm fine with like just a little linting
and maybe some like modularity review
once a week and in other use cases it
might just not be enough for me and I
really want to look at everything.
>> Can multiple agents coordinate within a
harness?
>> So I was talking before about the coding
harness itself is the the base thing
that does everything right and that
coding harness might actually have the
ability to spin off multiple agents
>> and then my expanded harness like I can
of course you know all of those agents
can potentially access it or some of
those agents might be part of my harness
my expanded harness. So like there might
be a code review agent that is one of my
sensors. So yeah, again with the
terminology it's a little tricky
[laughter] right now, but I think we're
getting there. It's getting a little
better. I would love it if there was a
better word for this expanded outer
harness, but nobody has come up with one
yet. So I think it would be helpful if
we had a separate word for it. That
outer part of the onion basically that
we engineer. Yeah. And these separate
code review agents are actually a very
very common sensor that people set up
where they spin off another sub agent
that has its fully owned context and no
history of the conversation and then
with that quote unquote unbiased view it
looks at the code and reviews it.
Sometimes people like to use a different
model even for that sub agent right and
so that's like a very commonly used
sensor that people put in place. In your
article, you talk a little bit about the
role of human in the software
development life cycle and also the
accountability which humans have to do
things right which agents might not have
because they don't belong to an
organization or have an organizational
>> Yeah. They they definitely don't. They
are machines, right? They don't have
accountability. Yeah. [laughter]
>> So now we're placing so much of trust on
these agents to do a lot of the work
without [clears throat] the
accountability. So how does this whole
fit into the software development life
cycle?
>> Yeah. And also to add to that sometimes
like some of the anecdotes and stories
you hear it's also putting people in an
unfair position because some
organizations on the one hand side put a
lot of pressure on people to use coding
agents and to become faster and more
output and you're you know you're being
measured by that. But then as when
something goes wrong then suddenly it's
your fault. But when you put a lot of
pressure on people, oh, now that you
have AI, you have to be X% faster, you
have to create 50 PRs a week or
whatever, right? Then you know if that's
what you're being measured on, people
are going to cut corners and it's going
to lead to more incidents. It's going to
lead to more instability, right? like
Google does this Dora report on software
delivery performance and now they're
also focusing a lot on the AI assisted
they call it I think AI assisted
software delivery and that is one of the
factors that they have found so far in
their data that instability goes up
right so or stability goes down however
you want to put it and yeah there were
some like prominent incidents over the
past few months where in the
communication around it you could start
seeing some organizations having this
reflex to throw people under the bus a
little it right and so I'm always torn
because on the one hand it's like
absolutely clear to me the human has to
be accountable right but because of the
environment that we put the agents in
and that we put people in I feel for
people for cutting corners when you're
only being measured by activity by
throughput and all of that so it's a
tough situation I think it has to be
done consistently if you still expect
accountability like if you hold humans
accountable for what's happening you
also have to give them the space the
environment and the incentive to be able
to do that.
>> That's true. So in this regard, I also
wanted to ask you from your perspective,
how is the role of the software
engineering change because of
>> agents, coding agents and harness
engineering? How does the whole thing
change?
>> Yeah, I mean from the beginning of all
of this hype starting, right? Like
people have said, oh, it's just we we
don't type the code anymore, right? I
mean, that's what people mean these days
when they say, oh, all of our code is
written by AI or 90% of our code is
written by AI. They mean it's being
typed by AI, right? Of course, a lot of
it is also reasoning about and creating
it. But the engineer sitting in front of
the coding agent or like deciding what
task they give it, how they describe
like a lot of the prompting that is
being done is very technical, has a lot
of technical details, right? And this is
particularly easy for experienced
software engineers, right? Because when
we know what we need ultimately and what
good looks like, we're also a lot better
at prompting and saying what we need,
right? So, but there from the beginning
in this talk of like, oh, the
abstraction level goes up, right? But I
don't think it goes up in the same way
that went up with compilers and stuff
like that. It's like a typical
comparison that people do. Oh, it's like
at some point at first people didn't
trust assembly code and then at some
point they just trusted it and never
read it again, right? But I don't think
it's the same thing because a large
language model is not a compiler. A
compiler is repeatable, deterministic to
like very very high nines. So, and a
large language model is very semantic,
interpretative, probabilistic, all of
those types of things. So, I think it's
a different type of abstraction level
raising that will happen here. I also
think that the details will matter less,
especially when we find good ways to
control the details even more with tools
like linting and stuff like that. But
then, you know, like I said, this
modularity review, that's already where
I came to the point where just having
the data and the computational sensors
was not enough anymore. You needed more
semantic interpretation, which an LLM
helps us with a little bit. But then we
also maybe want to look at and still
understand what's going on in our
codebase. So, it's easier for us again
in the future to tell the LLM what we
need. So, yeah, I think there's
definitely some kind of raising of the
abstraction level, but we don't know yet
where that's going to sit. might also
depend on the domain. And then the other
thing is this thinking and risk
assessment that I talked about before.
So I recently thought about the best
quality analyst I ever worked with who
was actually a career changer from
recruiting. So not a computer science
graduate. She could sit with us
developers and she got into coding a
little bit and she could sit with us.
She could read the code and she was the
person on the team who understood the
whole system inside out better than
anybody else on the team. And she would
know when we would do story kickoffs,
she would say things like, "Oh, you're
changing something in the database." And
then she would know exactly what to poke
at, what to test, what the risk profile
of that was, what that meant. And so
this type of thinking in like, oh, we're
changing this, so that means that we
have to test and quality assure these
things. and maybe do we have sensors for
this whatever right so this type of risk
assessment or also how much do I review
based on probability impact
detectability that's something that will
be a very important skill and that often
developers haven't honed that much the
fact that we need to have quality
analysts on teams tells us that we've
seen so many teams go oh we need a
quality analyst you know there's like
six developers sitting there and they
all say they need a quality analyst so
it tells us that it's not like a a skill
that so far we've
always like widely developed. So that's
another shift I think we'll have to
make. Like you said before, how do I
know when I can trust it? It depends. So
I think that's a good skill like looking
at quality engineering. I mean, which we
used to have before, but then we've all
fused into the T-shaped engineer, but I
think that looks like this has to come
up a bit in the T-shaped. Yeah.
>> To highlight that again and quality
assurance in is very very much about
risk assessment. where are the critical
paths like what actually matters the
testing pyramid how will that change
right will we indeed have more
acceptance tests and then how do we feel
about the risk of that right and so on
so it's very much this risk assessment
and thinking and probabilities and being
comfortable with that
>> yeah I think the quality angle is going
to become all the more important when
writing code is not going to be so tough
so yeah
>> and then now we're also like to
determine quality we actually have to
describe what good looks like for our
situation
>> right
>> and That's also not something that we're
historically always good at.
>> Yes.
>> It's like, oh, it just feels more clean,
you know? So,
>> yeah. Metrics for that as well. Yeah.
I'd like to end the show by asking you a
little about what do you think about the
future of harness engineering, adding,
you know, things to make the AI agents
more predictable, right? Can you talk a
little bit about that? Yeah, I mean it's
just like maybe recency bias, but I've
been experimenting a lot with these
sensors because I think they're still
quite underused and there's also not a
lot of tooling in that area. I just
don't see the future as being like 50
markdown files in our codebase. I mean
that can't be it, right? And then like I
said before in every markdown file we
very important do the following. Never
do the following. I mean that can't be
it. Can we still call ourselves
engineers if that's how we're doing
stuff? [laughter] I don't know. I mean
we'll be part of that definitely but
yeah. So I'm like just like really
interested in like this whole ecosystem
and all these integrations into the base
harness and how we can make that better
and also balance it right. It also
cannot be just like throwing 100 tools
at the agent and like 50 sensors that
kind of overload it or we can think
about okay if I have these sensors do I
need those guides anymore? How do we
balance that? Yeah. And unfortunately
then we'll probably never have a really
really good way to measure what's better
and what's worse. So it will be about
the feeling again, right? But in short,
like I see a lot of tooling potential
there still and a lot of things we still
have to figure out about how to balance
this like this whole idea of regulation.
I really like it like a system that you
try to regulate that it doesn't get too
much or too little or you know so I
really like that image to think about
harnesses
>> and it's also a good way to test the
models which are coming out in the
market as well right if you have a good
harness
>> if we know how to determine that it is
good then it's
>> okay [laughter] okay okay yeah you're
right I mean in the sense that you
>> all of those moving pieces right
>> right
>> it's all of these moving pieces the
models change the base harnesses change
I mean they're all like turnurning out
releases like crazy, right? And then our
own harness changes, right? So there's
so many moving pieces on the board. I
mean, the ultimate measures we have are
our software delivery performance,
right? What is stability? What is
throughput? And then the ultimate
ultimate measure is user value, right?
Like is this actually what we're
building? Are we just building more crap
faster or is it actually bringing the
users value? Is it bringing us revenue?
Is it bringing profit? Right?
>> I think building something of value is
what is most important. And I think yeah
using all the tools we can to get to
that state is what we should aim for.
Yeah. Thank you. This has been a very
great conversation. Where can people
find you in cyerspace?
Is it
>> LinkedIn or email?
>> Yeah. Most of my writing I do on my
colleague Martin Fowler's website
there's a series there exploring genai
and also some articles. I have a
personal website bitta.info info where I
just always list all the podcasts, the
YouTube conference, talks, writing, just
a list of content.
>> Okay, great. I'll add that to our show
notes. Thank you for coming on the show.
>> Yeah, thanks for the conversation,
Priyanka.
>> This is Priyanka Ragin for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net. net to
provide feedback. You can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
[music]
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
[music] License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.